Critical Labs, a company that makes
computers that run on human brains, is
opening up a data center in Singapore,
which they hope to house 1,000 units.
Yes, that is CL1 or clone, the only
computer that I know of that runs
computation off of human brains.
The research is moving alarmingly fast,
but it's really interesting. Biological
neural networks are a real competitor
for AI and they have a lot of
advantages, including being able to
grow. Computers are static, they can't
heal, but if you run it off of lab-grown
brain tissue, well, that is something
that can heal. However, the research
seems to be incorporating biological
neural networks into AI, which I
actually hate calling them biological
neural networks. I prefer to call them
organoids. VNNs have also moved to being
two-dimensional because they're just a
lot easier to work with. You can diffuse
oxygen and nutrients alongside them, and
I guess if part of it expires, you're
going to have to cut out that little
portion of it. With brain organoids, you
can actually replace the node that has
expired.
This is a method I really haven't seen
before. Usually, when you think of
organoids in AI as biohybrids, they put
the brain organoids in charge of the AI
to give it something like agency, but
they went the entire other direction and
it seems it works.
Oftentimes with these kinds of
intelligent systems, you'll have
multiple organoids to a chip and they'll
be able to communicate with each other
through axons. And if one expires, you
could hypothetically pop a new one in
and a new organoid could train the old
organoid. I see some interesting ways to
go around it. So, when the new organoid
comes in, it just doesn't know
everything that the other organoids know
at that point. That's what makes these
systems useful, that they get better at
their tasks over time. So, having
something, you know, expire is kind of a
hit to the system. Or you can do what
these guys did, which is train an AI to
behave like a biological neural network,
know when to shock them and where and
how to operate them, and let that one
interact with it, which seems to save a
lot of time.
You can see how the brain organoids
behave and these are going to be their
firing patterns. You just see
spontaneous activity prior to learning.
That's because they're just firing
randomly.
And then you can see the very stark
contrast when they start learning and
then they have post training where they
learn to do their task. Because they're
trained on dopamine or ordered and
disordered signals, they tend to prefer
order and dislike disorder. They have a
preference. That means that they can
engage in goal-directed activities in
which they have something that they want
to accomplish because they will get a
reward and avoid punishment.
For this reason, some researchers have
claimed sentience, although that is a
point of contention because sentience is
something that we simply cannot
demonstrate perhaps ever. How do we
determine that something is having an
experience?
Either way, we are getting to the point
where these can replace a lot of the
traditional ways that we use AI and they
can be incorporated into things like
Python script.
While AI requires massive data centers
that use a huge amount of electricity,
these are significantly less power
hungry, but we are still figuring out
how to get them to work effectively.
I mean, CL1 lasts you about 6 months at
most and that is a great improvement
from earlier kinds of organoid systems
that would last roughly 1 month.
Some people have managed to keep them
alive for 5 years or more. The only
reason that it was 5 years is because
that's when the experiment ended. We
could potentially keep brain organoids
alive indefinitely, but it's difficult.
You will have to have a system that has
no contamination whatsoever because they
lack an immune system and if you manage
that, you have to make sure they don't
eventually expire of hypoxia, which is
one of the benefits to two dimensions.
Hypoxia and circulation is really not
that much of an issue. One of the issues
that you will have is that if you cloned
human brain organoids, you are moving
from something that is essentially fetal
and it's still going to go through the
process of aging just like our brains.
Meaning, these guys are not a static
system. Things change over time and
organoids age, too. I imagine once we
really get the hang of it and we can
keep these guys around for 70 or more
years, there will be a point in which
your computer's computation system just
gets old. We're not at that point yet.
First, we have to optimize the system. I
wonder if anyone is going to figure out
the exact age at which organoids
function optimally. I wonder if it's
like 5 years old or not. I think I want
to make a longer video on how we got to
this point, the benefits and drawbacks
of each method for trying to get
intelligence out of a brain organoid.
Because to me it is fascinating. Us
humans started with trying to get
intelligence out of slices of postmortem
brains, and then we figured out that we
could grow them. And now that us humans
have grown them, we're now growing them
in two-dimensional form so they can be
computers. And interestingly, with
advancements in keeping brain organoids
alive, some research groups have been
trying to get intelligence out of
postmortem human brains again. There's
reasons you would want to do it, and I
really want to talk more about it.
Either way, I will keep you up to date.
You really don't have a choice. I hope
you've enjoyed this. Follow for more.